<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="core">
	<title>Core component</title>
	<para>
		The core component of the Web:Extend framework represents a set of classes,
		constants and functions defined upon inclusion of the core file, <filename>wee/wee.php</filename>.
		The core of the framework is very minimalist, initializing only what is required by other modules to work correctly.
	</para>
	<para>
		You can load Web:Extend using the following code:
		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-load.php.xml"/>
	</para>
	<para>
		The framework version can be obtained through the <literal>WEE_VERSION</literal> constant.
	</para>
	<para>
		The format of the version is compatible with PHP's <ulink url="http://php.net/version_compare">version_compare function</ulink>.
		You can determine if the current version of the framework is the one you need by using the following snippet:
		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-version.php.xml"/>
	</para>
	<para>
		If <ulink url="http://php.net/security.magicquotes">magic quotes</ulink> are enabled,
		the framework will automatically disable them and remove all the magic quotes from the input data.
		We recommend however that you disable it directly in the PHP configuration file if possible.
	</para>

	<sect1 id="core_predefined">
		<title>Predefined classes, constants and functions</title>

		<sect2>
			<title>Classes</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><literal>weeAutoload</literal>: <link linkend="core_autoload">see the autoload documentation</link></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>weeException</literal>: <link linkend="core_exceptions">see the exceptions documentation</link></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Constants</title>
			<para>
				Apart from the framework's version, a few other constants are defined.
				Some can be overridden while others are defined depending on the context.
			</para>
			<para>
				These constants are defined only if they are not yet defined.
				This means you can override their default value if you define them before loading the framework.
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><literal>APP_PATH</literal>: path to the application's root based on the requested URI</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>ROOT_PATH</literal>: path to the application's root in the filesystem (the folder containing the bootstrap file <filename>index.php</filename>)</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>PHP_EXT</literal>: extension for PHP files; defaults to <literal>'.php'</literal></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>CLASS_EXT</literal>: extension for PHP class files; defaults to <literal>'.class' . PHP_EXT</literal></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				These constants are defined depending on the environment.
				You cannot override them.
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><literal>WEE_CLI</literal>: defined if the script was called from the command line</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>WEE_ON_WINDOWS</literal>: defined if the script is running on Windows</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Functions</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><literal>_T</literal> and <literal>_WT</literal>: <link linkend="core_nls">see the native language support documentation</link></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>array_value</literal>: shortcut for <literal>if (isset($a['key'])) return $a['key']; else return 'default';</literal></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>burn</literal>: safely throw an exception (<link linkend="core_exceptions">see the exceptions documentation</link>)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>rmdir_recursive</literal>: recursively remove a directory</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>safe_header</literal>: same as <literal>header</literal>, but also prevent attacks like HTTP splitting and header injections</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>safe_path_info</literal>: returns a correct PATHINFO based on many parameters</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>xmlspecialchars</literal>: convert special characters to XML entities</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>weeLog</literal>: <link linkend="core_log">see the log function documentation</link></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Interfaces</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><literal>Mappable</literal>: defines the method <literal>toArray</literal> returning the array representation of the object</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><literal>Printable</literal>: defines the method <literal>toString</literal> returning the string representation of the object</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="core_autoload">
		<title>Autoload</title>
		<para>
			Autoload allows you to use files without including them; in fact they are automatically included on the fly.
			It is a PHP feature that will run callback functions everytime an unknown class is encountered.
			These function then try to locate and load the required file on the fly, without the developer having to include it herself.
			For more informations about this feature, see the <ulink url="http://php.net/autoload">PHP documentation</ulink>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Web:Extend provides its own autoload handler in the weeAutoload class.
			<literal>weeAutoload::loadClass()</literal> is called every time a class needs to be loaded.
			For example, <literal>weeAutoload::loadClass('weeForm')</literal> will include the file <filename>wee/form/weeForm.class.php</filename>.
		</para>
		<para>
			To add a path to autoload, you can use <literal>weeAutoload::addPath('/path/to/autoload')</literal>.
			You can add this call in your bootstrap script (e.g <filename>index.php</filename>), just after <literal>require('wee/wee.php');</literal>.
			All the files named <literal>CLASSNAME.class.php</literal> with <literal>CLASSNAME</literal> the name of the class defined in the file will be loaded automatically.
		</para>
		<para>
			weeAutoload will scan every directory which has been passed to its <literal>addPath()</literal> method and build a map from classnames to filenames.
			Since scanning all these directories is a very intensive operation, Web:Extend will cache the listing of the files found during the first scan.
			On all subsequent requests, the cache file will be loaded directly.
		</para>
		<para>
			The cache file is located by default at <filename>app/tmp/autoload.php</filename>.
			If you wish to change this path, you can define the constant <literal>WEE_AUTOLOAD_CACHE</literal>
			in your bootstrap script (e.g <filename>index.php</filename>) and set it to the path you need.
		</para>
		<para>
			The cache is enabled by default, unless <literal>DEBUG</literal> is defined.
			This allows you to not have to worry about enabling the cache on production servers or disabling it while developing.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you need to disable the cache without enabling <literal>DEBUG</literal>,
			you can either comment <literal>WEE_AUTOLOAD_CACHE</literal> or define the constant <literal>NO_CACHE</literal>.
			Keep in mind that disabling caching will greatly reduce the performances of your application.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="core_exceptions">
		<title>Exceptions</title>
		<para>
			Web:Extend uses various exceptions for error handling, including SPL exceptions and a few others.
			The exceptions thrown by a function are listed in its docComment and can be found in the API.
			It is good practice to catch these exceptions and display a meaningful message to the user.
			If you don't, however, Web:Extend will handle it, as described in this article.
		</para>
		<para>
			There's 2 kinds of exceptions: logical and runtime.
			The logical exceptions are thrown when something is wrong with the application itself. For example: a parameter has a wrong type.
			The runtime exceptions can only be detected at runtime: for example the user sent an unexpected value.
		</para>
		<para>
			The following two tables contain all the exceptions used by the framework (but not necessarily defined by default).

			<table>
				<title>Logical exceptions</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Name</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>BadFunctionCallException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when a function call was illegal.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>BadMethodCallException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when a method call was illegal.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>BadXMLException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when an XML doesn't follow strictly its DTD schema.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>DomainException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception that denotes a value not in the valid domain was used.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>DoubleFaultException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown in the exception handling code.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>FileNotFoundException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when a required file is missing.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>IllegalStateException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when a method is called and the object isn't in the right state (example: not initialized).</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>InvalidArgumentException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception that denotes invalid arguments were passed.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>LengthException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when a parameter exceeds the allowed length.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>OutOfRangeException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when an illegal index was requested.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

			<table>
				<title>Runtime exceptions</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Name</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>ConfigurationException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when a configuration requirement is not met.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>DatabaseException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when there is a database error.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>EndOfFileException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when an end of file is reached.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>NotPermittedException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when permission requirements are not met.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>OutOfBoundsException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown when an illegal index was requested.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>OverflowException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown to indicate arithmetic/buffer overflow.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>RangeException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown to indicate range errors during program execution.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>UnderflowException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown to indicate arithmetic/buffer underflow.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><literal>UnexpectedValueException</literal></entry>
							<entry>Exception thrown to indicate an unexpected value.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</para>

		<sect2 id="core_exceptions_default">
			<title>Default exception handling</title>
			<para>
				By default, Web:Extend will catch all exceptions and print an error page.
				The framework also transforms any triggered error in an <ulink url="http://php.net/errorexception">ErrorException</ulink> which are then catchable like any other exception.
				The error page contains generic information about the error and a few instructions to help the user of the application.
				In <literal>DEBUG</literal> mode, the page will also contains a detailed report on the error, including a trace, if available.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can customize the error page and set up your own instead of the generic one.
				To do this, simply call <literal>weeException::setErrorPage</literal> with the path to the error page file.
				This file will then get included, which means it can be a PHP script or just a simple HTML file.
				It will also be provided with <literal>$aDebug</literal>, an array containing debugging informations.
				You are free to use it or to ignore it.
			</para>
			<para>
				Here is an example calling this method:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-seterrorpage.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The <literal>$aDebug</literal> array contains the following values:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><literal>type</literal>: either <literal>'error'</literal> or <literal>'exception'</literal></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>name</literal>: name of the error/exception</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>message</literal>: description of the problem</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>trace</literal>: complete trace leading to the uncatched exception</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>file</literal>: the file where the error occurred</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>line</literal>: the line where the error occurred</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>number</literal>: only for errors; the error's number</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can take a look at the default error page located at <filename>trunk/res/wee/error.htm</filename> for a detailed example using this array.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Safely throwing exceptions</title>
			<para>
				Avoid throwing exceptions directly using the <literal>throw</literal> keyword.
				If you make a typo in the exception's name, it will result in a fatal error.
			</para>
			<para>
				The framework defines the <literal>burn</literal> function for throwing exceptions.
				It takes two parameters: the exception name and the error message. If the exception doesn't exist, a <literal>DoubleFaultException</literal> is thrown instead.
				If you really need a script to finish properly, catching <literal>Exception</literal> directly will ensure there is no problem, even if you made a typo.
			</para>
			<para>
				A few examples:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-burn.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Catching PHP errors</title>
			<para>
				As explained before, when an error is triggered, the default error handler throws an <ulink url="http://php.net/errorexception">ErrorException</ulink>
				with the same informations as the triggered error. The default error handler totally ignores the error level set through
				<ulink url="http://php.net/error_reporting">error_reporting</ulink> so every catchable error is caught by it.
			</para>
			<para>
				The following snippet demonstrates how to catch PHP errors.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-errorexception.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Recommended practices</title>
			<para>
				The shut-up operator <literal>@</literal> should be used only in the following two conditions:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>If it makes more sense to throw a specific exception instead of <literal>ErrorException</literal>.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>If the target code must never fail. This condition should be very rare.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				It is a really bad practice to use it when combined with an instruction
				that might include or parse a PHP file, as it would mask the error and display a blank page.
			</para>
			<para>
				The following rules define how the developer can choose between the various exceptions:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>If under normal use of the class the script should be terminated upon encountering a PHP error then use <literal>ErrorException</literal>.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>If the normal use of the class may require the developer to catch an exception upon an error in a method and continue normally
					then use a normal exception instead of <literal>ErrorException</literal>. Example: <literal>FileNotFoundException</literal>, <literal>BadXMLException</literal>.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>If the normal use of the class require the developer to catch exceptions to determine if an action was successful, then use a custom exception
					for the class/module. Example: <literal>FormValidationException</literal>, <literal>AuthenticationException</literal>, <literal>RouteNotFoundException</literal>.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				Only for the last 2 cases the docComment should inform the developer of the exceptions that can be thrown by the function or method.
			</para>
			<para>
				There is no need to check for invalid arguments unless not doing so could result in an illegal state.
				For example, the checks done in <literal>weeAuthDbTable::__construct</literal> are important
				because without them invalid arguments would not prevent the construction of the object
				and yet the <literal>authenticate</literal> and <literal>authenticateHash</literal> methods would always fail,
				thus rendering the object useless.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="core_log">
		<title>Server log</title>
		<para>
			Web:Extend provides a simple function for logging: <literal>weeLog</literal>.
			<literal>weeLog</literal> will simply format the message according to <literal>WEE_LOG_FORMAT</literal> and send it to <literal>STDERR</literal>.
			Most web servers (including Apache or lighttpd) will automatically log everything that is sent to <literal>STDERR</literal>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Sending to <literal>STDERR</literal> ensures that your application will be as performant whether you log or not.
			There is no significant performance loss for logging messages using <literal>weeLog</literal>. You can use it safely in any application.
		</para>
		<para>
			When using the command line, you can easily manipulate <literal>STDERR</literal> and redirect it to a file, process it or simply ignore it.
		</para>
		<para>
			To log a message, simply use:
			<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-log.php.xml"/>
		</para>
		<para>
			By default, the log level will be <literal>'notice'</literal>.
			The message from our above example will look like this:
			<programlisting>
[Sun Nov 09 18:27:05 2008] [notice] [wee] Sending a message to the log file!
			</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			To change the level of the log message, simply add a second parameter. For example you could use the following to log an error:
			<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-log-error.php.xml"/>
		</para>
		<para>
			It will results in:
			<programlisting>
[Sun Nov 09 18:27:05 2008] [error] [wee] An error happened!
			</programlisting>
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Log format</title>
			<para>
				By default the error message is formatted using Apache's default log format.
				You can of course define your own format.
				To do so, simply define <literal>WEE_LOG_FORMAT</literal> in your boostrap file.
				For example you could use:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-log-format.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Where <literal>%c</literal> is the current time and date,
				<literal>%1$s</literal> is the message and <literal>%2$s</literal> the message level.
				The format string is passed through <ulink url="http://php.net/strftime">strftime</ulink> first so you can define the date format to your liking.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="core_nls">
		<title>Native language support</title>
		<para>
			Web:Extend provides two functions that can be used to translate an application.
			These functions are wrapped around the <ulink url="http://php.net/gettext">gettext extension</ulink>
			and provide a similar functionality. The framework also includes an alternative implementation
			of <literal>gettext</literal> written in PHP, in case the extension is not available.
		</para>
		<para>
			The translations functions of the framework handle both singular and plural form with the same function, as opposed to <literal>gettext</literal>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The functions are <literal>_T</literal> and <literal>_WT</literal>.
			The first function, <literal>_T</literal>, is used to translate the application's messages.
			This is the only function you should need when writing an application using the Web:Extend framework.
			The other function is used internally by the framework.
			It uses a different domain (and thus different localization files) than the application.
		</para>
		<para>
			The translation functions accept either one or three parameters.
			When passing only one parameter, the operation performed is equivalent to calling the <ulink url="http://php.net/function.gettext">gettext function</ulink>.
			When 3 parameters are passed, the operation is equivalent to calling the <ulink url="http://php.net/ngettext">ngettext function</ulink>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Assuming you have created a french locale file for your application, you can use the following code to switch to french and translate a few strings:
			<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-locale-sing.php.xml"/>
		</para>
		<para>
			Using the second form of the function requires a bit more work.
			Let's assume we have a variable named <literal>$iNumberOfPonies</literal>.
			We want to output <literal>pony</literal> if there's 0 or 1 pony, and <literal>ponies</literal> if there's 2 or more.
			This is done like this:
			<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/core-locale-plur.php.xml"/>
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>gettext</literal> manual has more examples for handling plural forms and multiple parameters.
		</para>
		<para>
			Web:Extend also provides a <link linkend="mod_l10n">complementary internationalization and localization solution</link>.
			With it, you can correctly format numbers and dates for every cultures, among other things.
		</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Options</title>
			<para>
				There are 3 options applicable to the translation functions.
				To change an option, simply define its constant.
				You must define them before loading the framework if you wish to change the default values.
			</para>
			<para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><literal>APP_LOCALE_DOMAIN</literal>: Domain used by the application.
					Defaults to <literal>app</literal>. The domain represents the name of the file used by the localization functions.
					For example, if you change the domain to <literal>example</literal>, the translation file will be called <filename>example.mo</filename>.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>APP_LOCALE_PATH</literal>: Path to the locale folder. Defaults to <filename>app/locale</filename>.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>WEE_TRANSLATE</literal>: If defined, it forces the use of the alternative <literal>gettext</literal> implementation,
					even if the PHP extension is available.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Translation files</title>
			<para>
				Web:Extend uses <literal>gettext</literal> files to store the translation strings.
				The file format and the associated utilities are described in the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gettext/manual/gettext.html">gettext documentation</ulink>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The locale files are stored in the <filename>app/locale</filename> folder by default.
				The name of the language files is <filename>app.mo</filename> by default.
			</para>
			<para>
				Using the default values, the locale files are stored as follow:
				<programlisting>
app/locale/en_GB/LC_MESSAGES/app.mo
app/locale/en_US/LC_MESSAGES/app.mo
app/locale/fr_FR/LC_MESSAGES/app.mo
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				To generalize, locale files are stored in <filename>path_to_locale/lang/category/file.mo</filename>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The language used by the application is defined using the <ulink url="http://php.net/setlocale">setlocale function</ulink>.
				Details may vary depending on your operating system, refer to the PHP documentation for more information.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
