<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="mod_http">
	<title>HTTP module</title>
	<para>
		The <emphasis>HTTP module</emphasis> contains all the classes directly related to HTTP.
		This includes <link linkend="mod_http_cookies">cookies</link>,
		<link linkend="mod_http_sessions">sessions</link> and <link linkend="mod_http_upload">file upload handling</link>.
		These classes encapsulate the <literal>$_COOKIE</literal>, <literal>$_SESSION</literal> and <literal>$_FILES</literal> superglobal arrays, respectively.
	</para>

	<sect1 id="mod_http_cookies">
		<title>Cookies</title>
		<para>
			Web:Extend provides a class that encapsulates the <literal>$_COOKIE</literal> array.
		</para>
		<para>
			The cookie class can be used both as an application driver or standalone.
			This chapter will explain both ways.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>With the application module</title>
			<para>
				You can create and access the cookies object using the application module.
				To do so, simply call <literal>weeApp()->cookies</literal>.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-cookies-app-create.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				By default the cookies object is created only when it is accessed.
				There is no overhead if you don't use it.
			</para>
			<para>
				The cookies object acts much like the <literal>$_COOKIE</literal> array.
				You can access your variables like you would with an array:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-cookies-app-access.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				By setting the value of <literal>cookies.path</literal> in the configuration file,
				you can change the path under which the cookies will be saved.
				By default the path used is the path to your bootstrap file (<filename>index.php</filename>).
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Without the application module</title>
			<para>
				If you are not using the application module, you can also create a standalone <literal>weeCookies</literal> object.
				Once created you can access your cookies exactly like you would with the <literal>$_COOKIE</literal> array. For example:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-cookies-no-app-create.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can also define the path under which the cookies will be saved.
				By default the path used is the path to your bootstrap file (<literal>index.php</literal>).
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-cookies-no-app-create-path.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				All cookies set by this object will be saved under <literal>/path/to/my/app/</literal>.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Setting cookies</title>
			<para>
				You can set cookies in two different ways.
				The simpler way is to use <literal>weeCookies</literal> like an array.
				The following code will send the cookie <literal>my_str</literal> with a value of <literal>egg</literal>.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-cookies-offsetset.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				This way does not allow you to specify the expiration time however.
				If you need to, you can use the method <literal>set</literal>.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-cookies-set.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				However these variables won't be available for this request.
				The cookies object do not store the variables you set:
				it sends them to the browser, which will send them back on the next request.
				So <literal>my_str</literal> won't be available until the next request.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Deleting cookies</title>
			<para>
				To delete a cookie, simply unset it.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-cookies-offsetunset.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The value will be available in the object for the duration of the request.
				The cookie will be deleted by the browser upon reception of the response headers.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_http_upload">
		<title>File upload</title>
		<para>
			Two classes are designed to help you handle file uploads.
			These classes allow you to iterate through all the files,
			look for errors and safely move the files to their destination.
			The first class, <literal>weeUploads</literal>,
			wraps around the <literal>$_FILES</literal> array and allows you to retrieve files.
			The second class, <literal>weeUploadedFile</literal>,
			gives you a set of methods to manipulate the uploaded files.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Files and arrays of files</title>
			<para>
				When you create an HTML file input widget, you need to give it a name that will be used to identify the file after the form is submitted.
				You can have either single or arrays of files. To receive only a single file, you do not need to do anything special.
				However if you want to receive an array of files all sharing the same name, you need to append <literal>[]</literal>
				to the name of all the HTML file input widgets that will upload files with a common name.
			</para>
			<para>
				In this chapter, <emphasis>arrays of files</emphasis> refer to this specific use of HTML names.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Accessing a specific file</title>
			<para>
				The class <literal>weeUploads</literal> provides methods to determine if a file has been uploaded and to retrieve it for later use.
				Note that even if a file has tentatively been uploaded, an error might have occurred and you still have to look for errors on the individual file.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-files-fetch.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Note that you can't use the method <literal>fetch</literal> on an array of files.
				However you can use the method <literal>exists</literal> on them.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Iterating through the uploaded files</title>
			<para>
				You can iterate through all uploaded files using <literal>foreach</literal>.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-files-foreach.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can also filter the files so that you would iterate only over a specific array of files using the method <literal>filter</literal>.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-files-foreach-filter.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Error handling</title>
			<para>
				Once you got your <literal>weeUploadedFile</literal> object, you need to check if the upload completed successfully.
				You can do so by using the method <literal>isOK</literal>.
				Then, if an error happened during the upload you can retrieve an error message using <literal>getError</literal>.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-files-geterror.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Retrieving file information</title>
			<para>
				Once you know that the file was uploaded successfully, you can retrieve information about it.
				The <literal>weeUploadedFile</literal> object provides a few methods and properties that you can use.
			</para>
			<para>
				Amongst them, of note are the <literal>getExt</literal> and <literal>getFilename</literal> methods.
				They allow you to retrieve the file extension and name, respectively.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-files-info.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Moving the uploaded file</title>
			<para>
				You can use the method <literal>moveTo</literal> to move the uploaded file.
				Additionally you can use the method <literal>fileExists</literal> to determine
				whether a file already exists at the location where you want to move your uploaded file.
				They both use the same arguments, allowing you to reuse directly the values you would use for <literal>moveTo</literal>.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-files-moveto.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Note that if the second argument isn't provided the original filename will be used.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Full upload handling example</title>
			<para>
				Here is a full example of upload handling code.
				This is a typical use of these classes so feel free
				to copy paste it directly in your projects before tweaking it.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-files-example-1file.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				And then the same code but for all uploaded files.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-files-example-manyfiles.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_http_sessions">
		<title>Sessions</title>
		<para>
			Web:Extend contains a class that wraps the <literal>$_SESSION</literal> array,
			adding security checks to prevent attacks like <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Session_fixation">session fixation</ulink>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The session classes can be used both as an application driver or standalone.
			This chapter describes both use, starting with the application driver way.
			Then you will learn how to store sessions in a table in your database.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>With the application module</title>
			<para>
				<literal>weeApplication</literal>, the application module, can create a session automatically.
				You just have to change a line in the configuration file.
				Edit the parameter <literal>start.session</literal> and set it to <literal>1</literal> like this:
				<programlisting>
start.session = 1
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				The framework will then create a <literal>weeSession</literal> object,
				initiating a session, each time a page is requested.
				You can then access this object by typing <literal>weeApp()->session</literal>.
			</para>
			<para>
				Autostarting the session isn't required though. You could very well leave <literal>start.session</literal> at 0
				and access <literal>weeApp()->session</literal> only when needed. If you do need to autostart it you should
				also enable the output buffering, because the session will create a cookie that needs to be sent before
				any output happens.
			</para>
			<para>
				The session object acts much like the <literal>$_SESSION</literal> array.
				You can access your variables like you would with an array, like this:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-sessions-set.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Of course if you have to put or retrieve a lot of session variables you can do the following instead, to diminish the size of your code:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-sessions-set2.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Without the application module</title>
			<para>
				If you are not using the application module, you can also create a standalone <literal>weeSession</literal> object.
				Once created you can access your session variables exactly like you would with the <literal>$_SESSION</literal> array.
				For example:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-sessions-no-app.php.xml"/>
			</para>

			<sect3>
				<title>Closing the session</title>
				<para>
					The session will be closed and the data will be stored upon destruction of the session's object.
					This is automatically done when the script ends, but you might want to close the session before that.
					You can close it by simply <ulink url="http://php.net/unset">unsetting</ulink> the object:
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-sessions-unset.php.xml"/>
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Obtaining the user's IP address</title>
			<para>
				Finally, <literal>weeSession</literal> also allows you to retrieve
				easily the user's IP address using the <literal>getIP</literal> method.
				Calling <literal>weeApp()->session->getIP()</literal> will return the IP address of the user.
				If the user is behind a proxy, it will be the forwarded IP address that will be returned, and not the proxy IP address.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Storing the session data in a database</title>
			<para>
				By default the session data is stored on the filesystem, each session containing an individual file.
				You might prefer storing sessions in a database for various reasons.
				One reason could be to improve security by making sure nobody can access your application's session data.
				Another could be because you need a cluster of web servers all sharing the same session data.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can use the <literal>weeSessionDbTable</literal> class in lieu of
				<literal>weeSession</literal> to store the session data in a database table.
				Its usage is the same but its creation requires two other parameters.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <literal>db</literal> parameter specify the <link linkend="mod_db">database driver object</link> that will be used to store the session.
				If it is not given then the default database <literal>weeApp()->db</literal> will be used instead.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <literal>table</literal> parameter defines the table in which the session data is stored.
				The following table definition can be used.
				You can customize the schema definition as you wish as long as you keep the column names unchanged.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-sessions-table.sql.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Compability with <literal>$_SESSION</literal></title>
			<para>
				While we do not recommend mixing the two, it is possible to use
				both <literal>weeSession</literal> and <literal>$_SESSION</literal> at the same time.
				For example, the following code will work:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/http-sessions-compat.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The creation of the <literal>weeSession</literal> object starts the session and do the security checks;
				then we use the <literal>$_SESSION</literal> array to set our session variables;
				and finally we output one of the variables using the <literal>weeSession</literal> object.
				It works because <literal>weeSession</literal> works directly on the <literal>$_SESSION</literal> array.
			</para>
			<para>
				It can be useful when converting code to Web:Extend.
				You can just replace the <literal>session_start</literal> code first,
				test that everything is still working, and then replace all the code that uses <literal>$_SESSION</literal>.
				Or include third party code that uses the <literal>$_SESSION</literal> array without having to modify anything.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
