<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="mod_db">
	<title>Database access layer module</title>
	<para>
		Web:Extend provides an unified interface to various databases, including MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQLite and Oracle.
		The unified interface allows you to access any of these database using the same PHP code,
		meaning you only have to learn it once in order to use it everywhere.
	</para>
	<para>
		Note however that the database access layer is <emphasis>not</emphasis> an ORM.
		Web:Extend lets you access the database directly and does not prevent you to use functionality that only exists in one of the DBMS.
		You are entirely free to use <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/8.3/static/arrays.html">PostgreSQL's arrays</ulink>
		or <ulink url="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.1/en/set.html">MySQL's sets</ulink>.
		This means you can freely use the full power of your DBMS.
	</para>
	<para>
		The database access layer provides an easy-to-use interface to your database.
		There is only four types of objects: the database object, the result set object, the row object and the prepared statement object.
		Both the database and the prepared statement objects are used to query the database,
		while the result set and the row objects are used to handle the results of <literal>SELECT</literal> queries.
	</para>
	<para>
		Handling results is really easy: the result set is an iterator, meaning you can use <literal>foreach</literal> directly on the object, like if it was an array of rows.
		Similarly, the row object acts like an array by implementing <literal>ArrayAccess</literal>.
		Note however that by default the rows are returned as arrays.
	</para>

	<sect1 id="mod_db_connection">
		<title>Connection</title>
		<para>
			You can connect to a database either manually or using the application module.
			This chapter will explain both ways.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>With the application module</title>
			<para>
				You only need to modify the configuration file in order to connect to a database.
				You only need to fill the connection settings that will be used to connect to the database when you first try to access it.
				Note that the framework will never connect to the database until you need it.
				If your script use the application module but do not access the database, it will not try to connect.
			</para>
			<para>
				The parameters can vary depending on the database driver.
				This chapter will explain how to connect to a PostgreSQL database.
				Examples may vary depending on the DBMS used.
			</para>
			<para>
				There is 5 parameters: the database driver used, the hostname, login name, password, and database name.
				The last 4 are common when connecting to a database.
				The first parameter is the name of the class used to access the database,
				and can be either of <literal>weePgSQLDatabase</literal> for <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</ulink>,
				<literal>weeMySQLDatabase</literal> or <literal>weeMySQLiDatabase</literal> for <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com">MySQL</ulink>,
				or any other driver available.
			</para>
			<para>
				You need to modify the following parameters in the configuration file:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-app-configuration.cnf.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Once the application is started you can access your database using <literal>weeApp()->db</literal>
				and start writing <link linkend="mod_db_query">queries</link>.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Without the application module</title>
			<para>
				To connect without the application module you need to create the database driver yourself.
				It takes an <ulink url="http://php.net/manual/en/language.types.array.php">associative array</ulink> containing the settings as a parameter.
				The parameters are the same 4 we already discussed, except their name do not include the <literal>db.</literal> part.
				This is demonstrated by the following example, where we connect to a PostgreSQL database:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-connection-no-app.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can then use the <literal>$oDb</literal> object to perform <link linkend="mod_db_query">queries</link> on your database.
			</para>
			<para>
				Please note that some drivers may not require all these settings defined, or require totally different settings.
				Please refer to the documentation for your database driver before trying to connect.
				There might also be optional, driver-specific settings that are documented in the drivers documentation.
			</para>

			<sect3>
				<title>Closing the connection</title>
				<para>
					You usually shouldn't need to close the connection, since PHP will close it at the end of the script's execution.
					But you might consider closing it yourself, if you are running a time-intensive or memory-intensive script
					and you do not need to have a connection open the whole time, to free up resources.
					You can do it by simply using <ulink url="http://php.net/unset">unset</ulink> on the database object, as in:
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-closing-connection.php.xml"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					This will effectively destroy the database object and close the connection.
				</para>
				<para>
					Note however that it is not possible to close the connection manually at this time using the application module.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_db_query">
		<title>Query</title>
		<para>
			Once you are connected to the database you can start executing SQL queries.
			This section explains how to directly query the database.
			For <link linkend="mod_db_statements">prepared statements</link>, please see the corresponding section.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you are not using the application framework, you can replace <literal>weeApp()->db</literal> by your database object for the examples in this chapter.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can query a database in various ways using Web:Extend.
			The following diagram summarizes the various methods discussed in this section:
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Database query methods</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject><imagedata fileref="dia/db-query.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase>Database query methods</phrase></textobject>
					<caption><para>Database query methods</para></caption>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>The <literal>query</literal> method</title>
			<para>
				You can write queries by using the <literal>query</literal> method of the <literal>weeDatabase</literal> object.
				If we wanted to fetch the last 5 articles from the table <literal>articles</literal>, that is how we would do it:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-query-simple.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				It's pretty straightforward. <literal>query</literal> lets you write any SQL queries without restriction.
				You could write standard SQL or write database-dependent SQL without having the framework complain.
				But let's face it, most queries need parameters.
			</para>
			<para>
				There are two methods to bind parameters to query automatically.
				You can use either question marks (<literal>?</literal>) or named parameters placeholders in your query,
				and give the parameters directly to the <literal>query</literal> method.
				Using each of these two methods your parameters are escaped automatically without you
				having to worry about <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL_injection">SQL Injections</ulink>.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can of course build a query with parameters manually.
				However it is not recommended, and there's a few things to know when doing this that we will describe.
				The preferred solution is using named parameters.
			</para>

			<sect3>
				<title>Named parameters</title>
				<para>
					Using named parameters is easy.
					You just have to use names preceded by a colon, like <literal>:id</literal>, <literal>:parameter</literal>,
					<literal>:art_date</literal>, or even numbers like <literal>:3</literal> in the query,
					and then pass an associative array as the second argument to the <literal>query</literal> method.
					The array will contain the names without the colon as keys, like <literal>id</literal>,
					<literal>parameter</literal>, <literal>art_date</literal>, <literal>3</literal>, and their respective associated values.
				</para>
				<para>
					For example let's fetch the article number 3 from our articles table:
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-query-np1.php.xml"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					Or if we assume that your frame is waiting for an <literal>id</literal> parameter using <literal>GET</literal>,
					you can simply type the following line without bothering whether the <literal>id</literal> parameter exists
					or whether there's other values in the <literal>$_GET</literal> array.
					The `query` method will just look for the <literal>id</literal> value, and if absent trigger an exception.
					But even if doing this is possible, it is recommended to filter the input
					before passing the <literal>$_GET</literal> array to the <literal>query</literal> method.
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-query-np2.php.xml"/>
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3>

				<title>Question mark placeholders</title>
				<para>
					Another method is to use question marks instead of named parameters.
					This might come in handy when you do simple queries with one or two parameters only.
					Instead of passing an associative array to the <literal>query</literal> method,
					you will give values directly after the query. Let's see with an example:
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-query-qm.php.xml"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					The first parameter will replace the first placeholder, the second parameter will replace the second placeholder, and so on.
				</para>
				<para>
					Beware of using this method: you must give a parameter two times if it appears in two places in the query.
					If that happens or if the query uses a lot of parameters, please use the named parameters method.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3>
				<title>Manual query build</title>
				<para>
					You can also use the old way of building queries: by concatening yourself strings and values.
					This method is dangerous because the framework can't protect your queries from SQL injections.
					You should be very careful while doing this, and ensure that you always call the <literal>escape</literal> method for each parameter.
					Here's an example:
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-query-manual.php.xml"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					One more time, you shouldn't do this unless you have no other choices.
					If you stumble upon a case where you must do this, please submit a ticket
					and we'll try to enhance the framework so you won't have to do it next time.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>The <literal>queryValue</literal> method</title>
			<para>
				Sometimes you run a query only to retrieve a unique row which has only one column, for example to retrieve the count of a table.
				<literal>queryValue</literal> is a convenience method to facilitate using these values.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-queryvalue.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Retrieving the last primary key ID created</title>
			<para>
				After executing an <literal>INSERT</literal> query, you might need to retrieve an identifier for the row you just inserted.
				You can do so by calling the <literal>getPKId</literal> method.
				Depending on the driver this method will require a parameter: the name of the sequence for this primary key.
			</para>
			<para>
				This is an example for MySQL:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-getpkid-mysql.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				And the same example for PostgreSQL:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-getpkid-pgsql.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				With <literal>art_id_seq</literal> the name of the sequence associated with this column.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Retrieving the number of affected rows</title>
			<para>
				You might also want to check the number of affected rows after executing
				an <literal>INSERT</literal>, <literal>UPDATE</literal> or <literal>DELETE</literal> statement.
				Reasons might be because you want to check your query was executed successfully.
				You can call the <literal>numAffectedRows</literal> method to retrieve this number.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-numaffectedrows.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_db_results">
		<title>SQL results</title>
		<para>
			When you execute a <literal>SELECT</literal> statement with the <literal>query</literal> method,
			a <literal>weeDatabaseResult</literal> will be returned. It allows you to retrieve the results of the query.
		</para>
		<para>
			We can obtain a <literal>weeDatabaseResult</literal> object by running the following code:
			<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-query-simple.php.xml"/>
		</para>
		<para>
			If you are not using the application framework, you can replace <literal>weeApp()->db</literal> by your database object.
		</para>
		<para>
			Let's now see what we can do with those results.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Counting rows</title>
			<para>
				<literal>weeDatabaseResults</literal> implements the <literal>Countable</literal> interface.
				This interface makes us define a method, <literal>count</literal>, that returns an integer.
				In the case of a database query results, it will be the number of rows returned.
				The <literal>Countable</literal> interface allows us to give objects to the <literal>count($var)</literal> PHP function.
				The function will then call the method <literal>count</literal> and return the resulting value.
				See the <ulink url="http://php.net/count">count documentation</ulink> for more details.
			</para>
			<para>
				This allows us to get the number of rows returned by the query by writing the following code:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-count-rows.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Fetching rows</title>
			<para>
				Web:Extend provides 3 ways of fetching rows from a <literal>weeDatabaseResults</literal> object.
			</para>

			<sect3>
				<title>The <literal>fetch</literal> method</title>
				<para>
					The method <literal>fetch</literal> method is mainly used when you are getting only 1 row back from your query,
					which usually apply to all queries that includes an equivalent of the <literal>LIMIT 1</literal> statement.
					<literal>fetch</literal> will throw an exception if there is no row to fetch, making it not appropriate for use for iterating through rows.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can fetch a row using the following code:
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-fetch.php.xml"/>
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3>
				<title>The <literal>fetchAll</literal> method</title>
				<para>
					The method <literal>fetchAll</literal> method returns all the results as an array of associative arrays.
					It can be useful if you want to process some data from the results before passing it to another function, like a template for display.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can fetch all rows using the following code:
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-fetchall.php.xml"/>
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3>
				<title>Using <literal>foreach</literal></title>
				<para>
					The last possibility to retrieve rows is to use the <literal>Iterator</literal> capabilities of the <literal>weeDatabaseResult</literal> object.
					<literal>Iterator</literal> allows you to use <literal>foreach</literal> directly on the <literal>weeDatabaseResult</literal> object, like this:
					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-foreach.php.xml"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					You might consider reading the <ulink url="http://php.net/manual/en/language.oop5.iterations.php">PHP5 foreach documentation</ulink>
					to learn how it works and be more comfortable before you start using it.
				</para>
				<para>
					Most of the times you will pass directly the <literal>$oResults</literal> object to your template for display.
					Please read the <link linkend="mod_output_tpl">templates chapter</link> for more details
					about the interaction between <literal>weeDatabaseResult</literal> and the template,
					like the automated encoding of rows data, automagically preventing cross-scripting vulnerabilities.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="mod_db_results_rowclass">
			<title>Custom row class</title>
			<para>
				By default <literal>weeDatabaseResults</literal> returns an <ulink url="http://php.net/manual/en/language.types.array.php">associative array</ulink>
				containing the names/values of the fetched row. It is possible to define a class that will store the row and provide additional functionality not available in a PHP array.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can use the <literal>rowClass</literal> method to define the class that will store the rows data.
				You can use any class, as long as the constructor takes one array parameter.
				But Web:Extend also defines a base class for rows, <literal>weeDatabaseRow</literal>.
				This class implements <literal>ArrayAccess</literal> and <literal>Iterator</literal> to make it act like an array when needed.
				You can extend this class to add any method needed.
				You could for example add a method that will format the row data to your liking.
			</para>
			<para>
				When using <link linkend="mod_model">domain models</link>, you can use this method to automatically create instances of your model.
			</para>
			<para>
				You only need to do this to change the row class used by the subsequent retrieval operations:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-rowclass.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_db_statements">
		<title>Prepared statements</title>
		<para>
			Prepared statements are SQL statements that are only prepared once and then executed as many times as needed with different parameters.
			The statement and the data are sent separately, helping prevent <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL_injection">SQL injection</ulink> vulnerabilities.
			Their advantages and their possible uses may vary depending on the database driver you use.
		</para>
		<para>
			Prepared statements increase performance by checking that the query is valid only the first time it is received.
			If valid, the query will then be prepared so that it can be executed as fast as possible the subsequent times it is called.
			However, since the statement and the data are sent separately (which is a good and safe practice),
			this may create an overhead that will result in worse performance than sending queries directly.
			You can only be sure a prepared statement will increase performance by benchmarking it in the context of your application.
			However, you can be pretty sure a prepared statement will perform better if you have a thousand of the same <literal>INSERT</literal> query to execute in your script, for example.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Initialization</title>
			<para>
				The database class of your driver allows you to create a prepared statement.
				It will return an instance of <literal>weeDatabaseStatement</literal>
				that you can use to execute the statement as many times as you need.
				To obtain a prepared statement object and execute it, use the following:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-prepare.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Execution</title>
			<para>
				The statement object works pretty much like the database object itself.
				It contains all the methods you need to interact with the prepared statement.
			</para>
			<para>
				To execute a prepared statement, you need to call the <literal>execute</literal> method.
				The return value obey the same rules as the <literal>weeDatabase::query</literal> method:
				a <literal>weeDatabaseResult</literal> result object will be returned if the prepared statement is a <literal>SELECT</literal> query.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-prepare-return.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				As usual, you can chain the <literal>prepare</literal> and <literal>execute</literal> methods if needed.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-prepare-chain.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				If the query contains parameters, their values must be bound to the prepared statement through its <literal>bind</literal> method.
				You should note that prepared statements only work with named parameters, as opposed with standard queries.
				All database drivers use named parameters.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-prepare-parameters.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Of course the execution of these two snippets is different, even if the result is the same, as was explained earlier.
			</para>
			<para>
				The most common use of prepared statement is to create a query and then reuse it multiple times throughout your script.
				This is most useful in the case of <literal>INSERT</literal> or <literal>UPDATE</literal> queries.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-prepare-common-use.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Retrieving the number of affected rows</title>
			<para>
				When the prepared statement is an <literal>UPDATE</literal> or a <literal>DELETE</literal> query,
				you can use the method <literal>numAffectedRows</literal> of the statement object
				to retrieve the number of rows affected by the query like you would do with the database object.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/db-prepare-numaffectedrows.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
