<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="mod_app">
	<title>Application controller module</title>

	<sect1 id="mod_app_mvc">
		<title>MVC architecture</title>
		<para>
			Web:Extend can be used as an MVC framework. We implemented a derivative of the original MVC design.
			The biggest difference is the use of a <ulink url="http://www.martinfowler.com/eaaDev/PassiveScreen.html">passive view</ulink>.
			As you will soon understand, the architecture is very simple, with the various components being loosely coupled and modifiable easily without any effect on other components.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Separation of concerns</title>
			<para>
				The main advantage of this architecture is that it enforces the separation of the output, of the data access layer and of the application's processes.
				You probably already heard that you shouldn't mix HTML and PHP code? Well it's the same kind of separation.
			</para>
			<para>
				Under this architecture, the output is handled by the <emphasis>view</emphasis>, the data access layer is handled by the <emphasis>domain model</emphasis> and the application's processes are handled by the <emphasis>controller</emphasis>.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Data flow</title>
			<para>
				With Web:Extend, when a page is accessed by a browser, the request is redirected to the bootstrap file.
				This file is the entry point for all pages used by your application.
				It loads the framework and sends the request directly to the <emphasis>controller</emphasis>.
				The request is then translated and an event is generated from it.
				The event is then sent to another part of the <emphasis>controller</emphasis>: the frame.
				Frames are where you write the application's controller code and handle or respond to the events received.
			</para>
			<para>
				Depending on the event, you might have to send data to the <emphasis>domain model</emphasis>,
				retrieve data from it and send it to the <emphasis>view</emphasis>;
				or you might simply have to perform some calculations and send them directly to the <emphasis>view</emphasis>.
				There's no restriction. You don't have to use models if you don't need them, nor do you have to send output back if you don't need to.
			</para>
			<para>
				Here's a simplified diagram of the data flows occurring in the framework:
				<screenshot>
					<screeninfo>MVC data flow</screeninfo>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject><imagedata fileref="dia/app-dataflow.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
						<textobject><phrase>MVC data flow</phrase></textobject>
						<caption><para>MVC data flow</para></caption>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</para>
			<para>
				As you can see, the <emphasis>domain model</emphasis> stores or retrieves data;
				the <emphasis>controller</emphasis> receives, queries or sends data;
				and the <emphasis>view</emphasis> only receives data.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Dependencies</title>
			<para>
				By using this simple architecture there is very few dependencies between the different parts of your application.
				There is at most 2 dependencies: the <emphasis>controller</emphasis> depends
				on the <emphasis>domain model</emphasis> and on the <emphasis>view</emphasis>.
				There is no dependency at all between the <emphasis>domain model</emphasis>
				and the <emphasis>view</emphasis>, as evidenced by this diagram:
				<screenshot>
					<screeninfo>MVC dependencies</screeninfo>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject><imagedata fileref="dia/app-dependencies.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
						<textobject><phrase>MVC dependencies</phrase></textobject>
						<caption><para>MVC dependencies</para></caption>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</para>
			<para>
				The main advantages to this (besides simplicity) are that the <emphasis>domain model</emphasis> and the <emphasis>view</emphasis> can be tested independently.
				You need however to use <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mock_Object">mock objects</ulink> to test the <emphasis>Controller</emphasis> itself.
				But you'll find out that most of the time the operations performed by the controller are very, very simple.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_app_configuration">
		<title>Configuration</title>
		<para>
			Configuration is a central part of any project.
			It allows to externalize settings like database credentials or session settings or even how errors should be handled.
			Without using a central point for configuration, you would have to hard-code the values directly in your application.
			This is not a good thing, especially when the configuration settings need to vary from one host to another.
		</para>
		<para>
			There is a lot of ways to store configuration settings, PHP code, database table, files with various formats.
			In Web:Extend the configuration depends on a file.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>File format</title>
			<para>
				The format of the file is very simple.
				The settings are organized into pair/value combinations.
				Here is an example configuration file revealing the syntax and all the statements available.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-configuration.cnf.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Those files use Perl-like comments. Any line beginning with <literal>#</literal> is a comment.
				<programlisting>
# this is a comment
				</programlisting>
			</para>

			<sect3>
				<title>Include statement</title>
				<para>
					The include statements' syntax is fairly straightforward.
					To include a file, simply put its name next to the <literal>include</literal> statement, as parameter.
					If the file path begins with <literal>//</literal>, the path will be relative to <literal>APP_PATH</literal>;
					if it begins with <literal>./</literal>, the path will be relative to the current config file being parsed;
					otherwise it will be relative to the current working directory.
					In most cases, <literal>APP_PATH</literal> is the current working directory, but you shouldn't count on it.
					<programlisting>
include //relative_to_app_path
include ./relative_to_current_file
include relative_to_current_working_directory
					</programlisting>
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3>
				<title>Targets</title>
				<para>
					Target instructions permits the developer to configure the application conditionally,
					allowing some configuration settings to vary from one host or operating system to another.
					For example, you may have two environments, one for development and one for production.
				</para>
				<para>
					Your configuration file could look like this:
					<programlisting>
db.password                          = default_password
$(host dev.example.org).db.password  = a_pass_easy_to_remember_for_the_dev_environment
$(host test.example.org).db.password = a_fairly_secure_password
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					The second line will only be read by the application if the hostname matches <literal>dev.example.org</literal>.
					Otherwise it will be ignored. Same for the third line, it will only be read if the hostname matches <literal>test.example.org</literal>.
					It is good pratice to put the production value by default and to override the production settings by your specific environment's settings.
					The production value will only be overrided if there is a matching target.
				</para>
				<para>
					The general syntax for target instructions is as follow.
					<programlisting>
$(function [param1] [param2] [...] target).key = value
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					Instead of a key-value setting, you can also write an include statement to conditionally include another configuration file.
					<programlisting>
$(function [param1] [param2] [...] target).include //path/to/file
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					Here is a list of all supported targets:
					<table>
						<title>List of configuration targets</title>
						<tgroup cols="3">
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry>Function</entry>
									<entry>Parameters</entry>
									<entry>Description</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry><literal>os</literal></entry>
									<entry>None.</entry>
									<entry>Operating System name, e.g. <literal>NetBSD</literal>. The equivalent PHP call is <literal>php_uname('s')</literal>.</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry><literal>host</literal></entry>
									<entry>None.</entry>
									<entry>Hostname, like <literal>localhost</literal> or <literal>example.com</literal>. The equivalent PHP call is <literal>php_uname('n')</literal>.</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry><literal>phpver</literal></entry>
									<entry>None.</entry>
									<entry>The version of PHP which is executing the script. The function executed is <literal>php_version()</literal>.</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry><literal>extver</literal></entry>
									<entry>Name of the PHP extension.</entry>
									<entry>The version of the given PHP extension. The equivalent PHP function is <literal>php_version()</literal> with the name of the PHP extension as its argument.</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry><literal>sapi</literal></entry>
									<entry>None.</entry>
									<entry>The type of the interface running PHP. The equivalent PHP function is <literal>php_sapi_name()</literal>.</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</table>
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Configuration namespaces</title>
			<para>
				In our previous example, all the settings beginning by <literal>db.</literal> are part of the <literal>db</literal> namespace.
				You can retrieve values from the namespace either by retrieving a single value:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-cnf.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Or by retrieving the whole namespace as an array:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-cnf-namespace.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Note that the namespace's name is removed from the key name in the returned array.
				Here, the <literal>db.host</literal> value is stored in the <literal>host</literal> key of the returned array.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Application configuration</title>
			<para>
				Web:Extend provides a sample configuration file located in <filename>share/conf/sample.cnf</filename>.
				This file contains default values that you can use when starting a project.
			</para>
			<para>
				The application framework automatically loads a configuration file.
				The configuration file is the one specified by <literal>WEE_CONF_FILE</literal> which defaults to <filename>ROOT_PATH/app/conf/wee.cnf</filename>.
				You may want to change the location of this file.
				You can do it by manually defining the constant prior to calling <literal>weeApplication::instance()</literal> in your bootstrap file:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-define-conf-file.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The application module will initialize a few things after reading the configuration.
				It will look for the following parameters:
				<table>
					<title>Parameters for application configuration</title>
					<tgroup cols="3">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Default value</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><literal>app.timezone</literal></entry>
								<entry>None.</entry>
								<entry>The default timezone of the application.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><literal>app.toppage</literal></entry>
								<entry><literal>toppage</literal></entry>
								<entry>The default frame of the application.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><literal>app.autoload.path</literal></entry>
								<entry>None.</entry>
								<entry>A string of colon-separated paths to autoload. Paths starting with <literal>//</literal> are relative to <literal>APP_PATH</literal>.</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</para>
			<para>
				See the <link linkend="mod_app_routing">routing section</link> for information about the routing configuration parameters.
				See below for the driver-specific configuration parameters.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Application drivers</title>
			<para>
				A driver is an object defined in the configuration file for use in your application.
				It can be any class, as long as it accepts one parameter for its constructor.
				This parameter will be an array containing the configuration for the driver.
			</para>
			<para>
				To add a driver, simply add this to your configuration file:
				<programlisting>
mydriver.driver = myDriverClass
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can then access this driver in the following way.
				The driver will be automatically loaded the first time you try to access it.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-driver.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				To specify parameters for the constructor, simply add a few more lines in the configuration file.
				Everything under the <literal>mydriver.</literal> namespace will be sent to the constructor of the driver.
				<programlisting>
mydriver.driver = myDriverClass
mydriver.param = example parameter
mydriver.another = and another one!
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				The driver's object isn't created when the application starts,
				to prevent wasting resources on objects that won't be needed.
				However you might sometimes need one to be started for each request.
				To start it automatically, you can use the <literal>start.</literal> configuration namespace.
				For example, you could force start the driver <literal>mydriver</literal> defined earlier by adding this line to the configuration file:
				<programlisting>
start.mydriver = 1
				</programlisting>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_app_events">
		<title>Events</title>
		<para>
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Setup and access control</title>
			<para>
				Before a frame call an event method, it will always call the <literal>setup</literal> method.
				You can use it to check if an user is authorized to access this event, or to initialize objects used in all the events of the frame.
			</para>
			<para>
				If an user do not have authorized access to a frame or an event, you can throw an <literal>UnauthorizedAccessException</literal>.
				The frame will catch it and call the method <literal>unauthorizedAccess</literal> where you can handle the problem, redirect the user or create and send a new event.
				Note that you are not required to define this method. By default it will stop execution and output an error message.
			</para>
			<para>
				Both <literal>setup</literal>, the event methods and the <literal>unauthorizedAccess</literal> method
				receive an <literal>$aEvent</literal> parameter containing all the event information.
				It is recommended to access the GET and POST data from the event array instead of using <literal>$_GET</literal>,
				<literal>$_POST</literal> or <literal>$_REQUEST</literal>, as you can later need to send events to other frames from your code and specify GET or POST data.
			</para>
			<para>
				Following is an example of access control. Assuming the session variable <literal>is_admin</literal> identifies an administrator,
				the code will prevent non-administrators to access events on this frame, and will redirect them to the login page:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-frame.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Writing events</title>
			<para>
				The event methods usually handle three tasks:
				they perform an action depending on the event received (example: create an user account);
				they retrieve data from your persistent storage solution;
				and they send this data to the templates for output.
				The frame is responsible for the creation of the template and its subsequent output;
				note however that the template will be created automatically without you needing to write any code.
				To send data to the template, you must use the method <literal>set</literal>.
				For example, the following code will create a variable <literal>$nickname</literal> in the template, containing the string <literal>'essen'</literal>:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-frame-set.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="mod_app_events_tpl">
			<title>Template files</title>
			<para>
				By default, the template file used corresponds to the name of the class for the frame.
				For example, the <literal>myFrame</literal> template will use the file <filename>app/tpl/myFrame.tpl</filename> by default.
				You can customize this behavior by defining the <literal>$sBaseTemplate</literal> property.
				For example, the following frame will use the template file <filename>app/tpl/example.tpl</filename>.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-frame-basetemplate.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Another property can be used to change the template file.
				The <literal>$sBaseTemplatePrefix</literal> property will append a prefix to the <literal>$sBaseTemplate</literal> property.
				This allows you to define a folder under which all templates are to be found for all events of this frame and/or for all childrens.
				This is especially useful when you define a base class for a type of frames (for example, administration panel frames)
				and decide to put all the templates for these frames under an <filename>admin</filename> folder.
				To do this you simply have to define the prefix in the base class once and then inherit it, like this:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-frame-basetemplateprefix.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Forwarding events</title>
			<para>
				You can trigger other events easily, whether they're in the same frame or a different one.
				While you can use this to forward the event to the correct method, you shouldn't use it instead of a <literal>Location</literal> HTTP header.
			</para>
			<para>
				There is two different ways to trigger an event in the same frame as the current event.
				You can either call it directly, or using the <literal>sendEvent</literal> method.
				Calling it directly will bypass the authorization check and the call to <literal>setup</literal>.
				When calling it using <literal>sendEvent</literal>, if the authorization fails an <literal>IllegalStateException</literal> is thrown.
				You can see the two different ways to trigger an event from the same frame in this example:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-frame-sendevent-inside.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can trigger an event from another frame using <literal>sendEvent</literal>.
				The new frame will replace the current frame in the application, unless the event is given a <literal>noframeschange</literal> parameter.
				Here is an example of its usage:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-frame-sendevent-outside.php.xml"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_app_routing">
		<title>Routing</title>
		<para>
			<emphasis>Routing</emphasis> is the process of selecting paths in the controller.
			In Web:Extend, the controller is divided in 3 parts: the main controller, <literal>weeApplication</literal>; the frames; and the event within the frames.
			The main controller first receives the request, translate it into an event and then send it.
			Routing encompass the creation of an event (or translating it from the request received by the server) and its dispatch to the correct method.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can use the default routing as described earlier or you can use a custom routing mechanism.
			It allows you to customize the paths in the URL of your application and to translate these custom URL into valid routes.
			It is very similar to using <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/mod/mod_rewrite.html">mod_rewrite</ulink>, but is done in PHP directly.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Route translation</title>
			<para>
				Custom routes are applied when translating the event received by the server into an event.
				This translation happens in <literal>weeApplication</literal>, before the event is sent to your frames.
			</para>
			<para>
				Customizing the route is simply applying a regular expression to it.
				The regular expression is applied to the pathinfo of the request using <ulink url="http://php.net/preg_replace">preg_replace</ulink>.
				To specify a route, you have to give a regular expression and its replacement.
				The replacement must be a valid application route and will be used to determine the frame and event names.
			</para>
			<para>
				Routes are tested one by one iteratively. The first match will be used to translate the route.
			</para>
			<para>
				Since it is applied on the pathinfo, the query string of the request is not modified.
				However, if a query string is found on the replaced route, its parameters will overwrite the parameters from the query string if they share the same name.
			</para>
			<para>
				For example if you access the URL <ulink url="http://example.org/~worm?user=apple">http://example.org/~worm?user=apple</ulink>
				and you have the regular expression <literal>/^~(\w+)$/i</literal> and its replacement is <literal>viewuser?user=$1</literal>,
				then the resulting pathinfo will simply be <literal>viewuser</literal> and the value of <literal>$aEvent['get']['user']</literal>
				will become <literal>worm</literal> instead of <literal>apple</literal>. The worm <emphasis>eats</emphasis> the apple.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="mod_app_routing_failsafe">
			<title>Fail-safe routing</title>
			<para>
				Sometimes you might need to redirect all non-existing events to the default event.
				This can be done automatically simply by implementing the <literal>weeFailSafeRouting</literal> interface, like this:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-frame-failsafe-routing.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				All events reaching this frame will be redirected to the default event handler, except for the event named <literal>save</literal>.
				If you sent an event named <literal>update</literal> to this frame, for example, it will be handled by the default event handler.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Custom routes</title>
			<para>
				As we saw, routes are defined by the regular expressions and their respective replacement.
				All configuration variables under the <literal>route</literal> namespace will be retrieved
				to be tested as custom routes, in the order they are found in the configuration file.
			</para>
			<para>
				Regular expression and replacement are defined as follow in the configuration file:
				<programlisting>
route.regular_expression = replacement
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				The regular expression must not include the slashes and the pattern modifiers.
				The string <literal>regular_expression</literal> here literally translate to <literal>/^regular_expression$/i</literal>.
				The case insensitive modifier is applied to the regular expression, so <literal>REGULAR_EXPRESSION</literal> here is the same as <literal>regular_expression</literal>.
				The reason for this is because PHP class names are case insensitive too.
			</para>
			<para>
				If the pathinfo matches <literal>/^regular_expression$/i</literal>, then it will be replaced by <literal>replacement</literal>,
				which will create an event that will be dispatched to the default event handler of the frame named <literal>replacement</literal>.
			</para>
			<para>
				Take a look at these lines for a more complete example:
				<programlisting>
route.is = aboutus
route.~(\w+)/(\w+) = $2?user=$1
route.~(\w+)/(\w+)/(\w+) = $2/$3?user=$1
route.(\d{4})/(\d{2})/(\d{2})/(.*) = viewpost?year=$1&amp;month=$2&amp;day=$3&amp;uid=$4
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				The first line is pretty straightforward. When the pathinfo equals <literal>is</literal>, the event is sent to the <literal>aboutus</literal> frame.
			</para>
			<para>
				The second line matches words.
				A pathinfo like <literal>~essen/editprofile</literal> will translate to <literal>editprofile?user=essen</literal>,
				meaning the event is sent to the <literal>editprofile</literal> frame's default event handler.
				The value of <literal>user</literal> will be available through <literal>$aEvent['get']['user']</literal>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The last line can be used to format the URL of a blog post, for example.
				A pathinfo like <literal>2008/11/06/rowo-part-2-simple-is-easy/</literal> will be matched,
				and will translate to <literal>viewpost?year=2008&amp;month=11&amp;day=06&amp;uid=rowo-part-2-simple-is-easy/</literal>.
				All the variables from the query string will be accessible through <literal>$aEvent['get']</literal>.
			</para>
			<sect3>
				<title>Strict routing</title>
				<para>
					By default, if there is no match with a custom route, the framework will try to use
					the unmodified request to determine the frame and event names and dispatch the event.
					There is an option however which you can use to make sure only your defined routes will be valid.
					Simply activate strict routing in the configuration file by setting <literal>routing.strict</literal> to 1 instead of 0:
					<programlisting>
routing.strict = 1
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					When a request do not match any route, a <literal>RouteNotFoundException</literal> will be thrown.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="mod_app_taconite">
		<title>Taconite for AJAX integration</title>
		<para>
			Web:Extend includes a Taconite component that allows you to perform simple DOM updates against an XML document either server or client-side.
		</para>
		<para>
			Taconite is a method to perform multiple DOM updates with an XML document. This document contains instructions which describe the DOM updates.
		</para>
		<para>
			Here is an example of a Taconite document:
			<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-taconite-document.xml.xml"/>
		</para>
		<para>
			This neat document may be used to implement a pseudo real-time activity logger in a social network application.
			The user agent will then periodically checks the server for new activity and the user will see new items at the beginning of the list <literal>#log</literal> on the page.
		</para>
		<para>
			Web:Extend includes mechanisms to generate Taconite documents.
			It will send a Taconite document only if the context is <literal>xmlhttprequest</literal> and if you used Taconite, otherwise it sends the template file.
			When the context is <literal>http</literal> and you use Taconite anyway,
			the template will first be rendered as usual, and then the Taconite you sent will be applied to it server-side.
			This allows you to easily make an event compatible with both contexts without any need for duplicate code.
		</para>
		<para>
			We recommend using the Taconite mechanisms included in the framework with the <ulink url="http://jquery.com">jQuery</ulink>
			library for client-side processing, because it includes a <ulink url="http://malsup.com/jquery/form/">form plugin</ulink>
			and a <ulink url="http://malsup.com/jquery/taconite/">taconite plugin</ulink>, that will make using Taconite a real bliss.
			The jQuery taconite plugin will detect Taconite AJAX responses and act accordingly without you needing to do anything other than initiate AJAX calls.
		</para>
		<para>
			As the most common updates can be performed both server and client-side, this tool greatly reduces the need of specific and duplicate code for AJAX requests.
			If the user do not have javascript available, weeTaconite will gracefully handle the request by regenerating the page and applying any DOM update on the server-side;
			otherwise only the XML Taconite document is sent to the user which is then processed locally.
			This behaviour lighten the server charge in both processor time and bandwidth volume, as only the XML Taconite is returned.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Usage</title>
			<para>
				We're going to demonstrate Taconite first by writing an <literal>update</literal> link that will refresh a part of the page using AJAX.
				The event used to display the page and to update it will be the same.
			</para>
			<para>
				The following event will do the job for you.
				For this example we will only display and update the current date and time
				but know that you can update more than one thing at once.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-taconite-example.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The template <filename>example.tpl</filename> can look like this:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-taconite-tpl.html.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The template displays the date sent by the frame, and define an AJAX action whenever the update link is clicked.
				There's nothing else to do, Taconite will handle it automatically.
				Whenever an AJAX request will be sent to the <literal>example</literal> frame,
				a Taconite response will replace the contents of the <literal>#date div</literal> with the current date.
			</para>
			<para>
				Alternatively, you can also give a template to Taconite.
				This allows you to easily separate concerns and render the same template for both normal and Taconite response.
			</para>
			<para>
				Instead of simply giving the date as in the example above, we could give the contents of a template.
				We'll transform our example above to make it send the date through a template.
				I know, making a template only to display a date isn't that useful but it should showcase how it works without complicating the example.
			</para>
			<para>
				The main difference lies in the frame. Instead of giving the date we need to create a template and send its output:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-taconite-example2.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The template only has the date line to be changed.
				We just need to render the template instead of outputting directly,
				like you would do normally when separating concerns into different templates.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-taconite-tpl2.html.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The template <filename>the_date.tpl</filename> can then simply output the date.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-taconite-tpl2-the_date.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can also put the <literal>#date div</literal> inside the new template and
				use the <literal>replace</literal> transformation command instead of <literal>replaceContent</literal> in the frame.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Alongside forms</title>
			<para>
				You can also use Taconite to provide immediate feedback to users submitting form data.
				Let's take a look at our <literal>edit</literal> event, responsible for editing a specific resource of our application.
				The event is written pretty much like a <link linkend="mod_form">standard form handling</link> but we've added 3 lines for the AJAX specific code.
				The workflow is exactly the same however, as you can see.
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-taconite-example3.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The form could be output as follow in the template:
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/build/app-taconite-tpl3.php.xml"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				The header of the template is slightly different than before.
				We use jQuery's form plugin to process the form through AJAX.
				To do that we include an additional javascript file and initialize the plugin.
				No additional operations required.
			</para>
			<para>
				Every form submissions will be done using AJAX.
				The jQuery taconite plugin will detect Taconite responses and act automatically,
				replacing the form and the message with the information sent by the server.
			</para>
			<para>
				If the user doesn't have javascript support, the operations will be done server-side and the complete page will be returned modified accordingly.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Limitations</title>
			<para>
				There exists no real limitations client-side.
				You can pretty much use any transformation command you want.
				You can even use custom commands, so you would be able to send commands to start visual effects if you wanted to.
				Read the <ulink url="http://malsup.com/jquery/taconite/#extend">documentation about extending the taconite plugin</ulink> for more details.
			</para>
			<para>
				At the time of the redaction of this documentation,
				the server-side taconite processor suffers a few limitations compared to its javaScript client-side counterpart:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Only <literal>#id</literal>, <literal>//xpath</literal> and tags selectors are supported.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Multiple selectors cannot be specified using the comma operator.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Only a subset of the transformations commands of jQuery is supported.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				The supported transformation commands for server-side processing are listed in the following table.
				<table>
					<title>Server-side taconite supported commands</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Command</entry>
								<entry>Summary</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><ulink url="http://docs.jquery.com/Manipulation/after">after</ulink></entry>
								<entry>Insert content after each of the matched elements.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><ulink url="http://docs.jquery.com/Manipulation/append">append</ulink></entry>
								<entry>Append content to the inside of every matched element.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><ulink url="http://docs.jquery.com/Manipulation/before">before</ulink></entry>
								<entry>Insert content before each of the matched elements.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><ulink url="http://docs.jquery.com/Manipulation/prepend">prepend</ulink></entry>
								<entry>Prepend content to the inside of every matched element.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><ulink url="http://docs.jquery.com/Manipulation/remove">remove</ulink></entry>
								<entry>Remove all matched elements from the DOM.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><ulink url="http://malsup.com/jquery/taconite/#extend">replace</ulink></entry>
								<entry>Replace all matched elements with the given content.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><ulink url="http://malsup.com/jquery/taconite/#extend">replaceContent</ulink></entry>
								<entry>Replace content of every matched element with the given content.</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</para>
			<para>
				Feel free to submit patches to support new selectors and/or new commands!
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
