<appendix id="ap-contrib">
	<title>Contributing to Web:Extend</title>

	<sect1 id="ap-contrib-tests">
		<title>Testing Web:Extend</title>

		<para>The most immediate contribution anyone can make is by running
		the test suite on all environments they have available. The test suite
		will run without any configuration required, but will skip a large
		amount of tests if extensions aren't available. No need to worry about
		the ones you don't need though. The only thing you'll want to setup
		is the database that will be used for the database tests. To do so,
		just create a database named <literal>wee_tests</literal> and a user
		named <literal>wee</literal> with a password <literal>wee</literal>
		and give it full access to the <literal>wee_tests</literal>
		database.</para>

		<para>To launch the test suite, go to the Web:Extend folder and type
		the following line in your terminal:</para>

<screen>
$ <userinput>php tools/tests/maketests.php -f tools/tests/</userinput></screen>

		<para>Or alternatively if you have <command>make</command> available
		you can just type:</para>

<screen>
$ <userinput>make test</userinput></screen>

		<para>You should get a very long output, one line per test, with a
		summary at the end.</para>

		<para>If all tests pass, then it's all good! Feel free to tell us it
		worked for you. If it didn't though, you should submit a bug report
		to our issue tracker or send us an email at
		<email>wee-users@googlegroups.com</email>.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="ap-contrib-bugs">
		<title>Reporting bugs</title>

		<para>Feedback is the most important contribution you can make to the
		project. A good bug report includes an explanation of what you tried
		to achieve along with the error encountered. The error can be obtained
		by repeating the action with <literal>DEBUG</literal> mode enabled.
		This usually is more than enough for us to resolve the bug. In the
		case that this isn't enough and that we need to contact you, it is best
		that you also provide an email address where we can join you.</para>

		<para>We currently use the github issue tracking system. This is not
		a perfect solution, but until we have one that's what we'll be using.
		If you don't want to register an account just to report a bug, you
		can simply send an email at
		<email>wee-users@googlegroups.com</email>.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="ap-contrib-src">
		<title>Contributing source code</title>

		<para>All source code contributions are welcome. If you wish to add
		a feature to the framework, contact us first in case we already had
		plans. Patches can be sent directly to the issue tracking system or
		to <email>wee-users@googlegroups.com</email>.</para>

		<para>Later you will be able to create and manage your own addons.
		If you plan to do so in the future, you can contact us and work with
		us to setup the best addons manager for your purpose.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="ap-contrib-docs">
		<title>Improving the documentation</title>

		<para>You can improve the documentation in various ways. The simplest
		way is by sending us your feedback along with suggestions, by email to
		<email>wee-users@googlegroups.com</email>. We are interested in any
		kind of feedback.</para>

		<para>You can also contribute new material to the guide, by writing a
		new chapter or improving an existing one. It is best that you contact
		us before starting though, to avoid duplicating efforts.</para>

		<para>Finally you can write tutorials or tips on your own and send us
		the links; we will display them on the documentation page along with
		the official documentation.</para>

		<para>The documentation can also be translated.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="ap-contrib-l10n">
		<title>Translating Web:Extend</title>

		<para>Considering the framework is still in beta, we have no plans
		to translate the framework or this guide just yet. But since we
		will at some point, you should contact us if you are interested.
		Note that right now everything could change and it could become
		more work than for a stable release. If you are interested in
		translating Web:Extend eventually, contact us by email at
		<email>wee-users@googlegroups.com</email>.</para>
	</sect1>
</appendix>
