<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap-about">
	<title>What is Web:Extend?</title>

	<para>Web:Extend is a simple, modern, powerful PHP web framework.</para>

	<sect1 id="chap-about-history">
		<title>Project history</title>

		<para>The initial work on Web:Extend was performed summer 2005
		and focused on automating the creation, handling and validation
		of web forms. The source from this library went on to become
		Web:Extend a few months later and saw the addition of many other
		solutions to automate and simplify the development process of
		web applications.</para>

		<para>After becoming a framework, Web:Extend focused on harnessing
		the power of the <ulink url="http://php.net/spl">SPL</ulink> to
		simplify the writing of code. It also changed the error handling
		to use exceptions everywhere, and made use of autoload to eliminate
		the need to manually include files.</para>

		<para>More recently, the ability to query databases metadata was
		added. The scaffolding components were built on this mechanism,
		allowing developers for example to simply specify a table name
		to create a fully functional domain model, but also to create
		fully functional forms to interact with this table. In addition
		all the scaffolding components operate live on the database,
		meaning that any modification of a table while developing is
		immediately taken into account without requiring the developer's
		intervention.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-about-features">
		<title>Features</title>

		<para>Web:Extend focuses on simplicity. Simplicity indicates a state
		of clarity and straightforwardness. Simple concepts and situations are
		commonly easier to explain and understand than complicated ones. They
		allow the developer to become free from hardship, effort and
		confusion.</para>

		<para>Simplicity allows the developer to focus on the requirements
		of his project rather than on its implementation. The developer can
		focus on the business logic of his application rather than on technical
		details, which allows him to deliver a finished product much faster
		and at lower costs.</para>

		<para>In that end, Web:Extend includes the following features:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
				Code quality and correctness
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				Secure defaults
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				Minimal interface
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				Loose coupling
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				A passive view MVC pattern
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				Live scaffolding using the database metadata
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>To achieve this quality, Web:Extend has developed various tools,
		including a unit test suite designed specifically for the framework's
		needs and a grep engine capable of detecting many inappropriate uses
		of PHP and the framework.</para>

		<para>Another key feature is that Web:Extend has no hesitation to
		kill off or rewrite inadequate experimental code. Experimental code
		usually gets included in a beta release, is used by our developers
		in real projects, and depending on the feedback received may be killed
		off in the next release. An experimental addition that is too confusing
		always gets killed or rewritten.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-about-goals">
		<title>Goals</title>

		<para>At this point the Web:Extend core is very stable. The only
		changes planned are relatively small. Amongst the remaining tasks
		include improving support for various configurations and giving the
		developer better debugging tools.</para>

		<para>Work has begun on an optional extra library distributed with
		the framework. This library, <emphasis>weexlib</emphasis>, gives a
		set of functions and templates that can be readily used to speed-up
		development using the Web:Extend framework.</para>

		<para>Other additions will come under the form of addons. We are
		currently working on an addons manager that would allow anyone to
		easily install, update but also write and publish addons. At a later
		time an addons repository will be made available to everyone.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-about-target">
		<title>Target audience</title>

		<para>Web:Extend is targeted at experienced PHP5 developers. It can
		be used in many kinds of projects with various sizes and performance
		requirements. Being an open-source product licensed under the LGPL,
		it can also be used in commercial solutions as long as the license is
		respected.</para>

		<para>Its most common use will be for web application projects,
		websites, CMS, and the likes. Web:Extend has the potential to scale
		to a lot of traffic but currently hasn't been used in projects with
		more than a few hundred hits per second, so additional testing and
		tweaks are probably required in that domain.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-about-download">
		<title>Downloading Web:Extend</title>

		<para>Web:Extend can be downloaded from the project's github, either
		by cloning the repository or by downloading a release tarball.</para>

		<para>The current version of the framework can be retrieved using the
		following command:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>git clone http://github.com/essen/wee.git</userinput></screen>

		<para>By default you will have the latest source available, which is
		intended for development of the framework and not for production. You
		can however switch to a release tag by listing the tags available and
		picking the one you want. From the cloned folder:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>git tag -l</userinput>
wee-0.1.0
wee-0.2.0
wee-0.3.0
wee-0.4.0
wee-0.5.0
wee-0.6.0
# <userinput>git checkout wee-0.6.0</userinput></screen>

		<para>If you can't or don't want to use <application>git</application>,
		you can simply head over to the project's download page and pick the
		version you need: <ulink url="http://github.com/essen/wee/downloads">
		http://github.com/essen/wee/downloads</ulink>.</para>

		<caution>
			<para>It is highly recommended that you download the latest release
			as older versions may not contain all the enhancements and are thus
			not representative of the Web:Extend product today.</para>

			<para>Older releases might also not be supported anymore and could
			contain security vulnerabilities.</para>
		</caution>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-about-community">
		<title>The Web:Extend Community</title>

		<para>The Web:Extend developers rely on the community's feedback
		to improve the framework. Any feedback or queries from users is
		always considered and is responded to whenever possible.</para>

		<para>The Web:Extend developers can be contacted through various
		channels. We currently have an IRC channel and mailing lists, and
		can be contacted directly through github either using the issues
		tracker or by private message. Based on feedback received, a user
		wiki will also be opened in the near future.</para>

		<para>The IRC channel is <literal>#webextend</literal> on
		<literal>irc.freenode.net</literal>. All other community outposts
		can be found by browsing the project's website available at
		<ulink url="http://extend.ws">http://extend.ws</ulink>.</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
