<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap-install">
	<title>Installing Web:Extend</title>

	<sect1 id="chap-install-req">
		<title>Requirements</title>

		<para>Web:Extend currently requires PHP 5.2. It may work with older
		versions of PHP but they are not officially supported so we cannot
		provide any guarantee.</para>

		<para>Web:Extend requires the following extensions:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
				A database extension (recommended:
				<ulink url="http://php.net/pgsql">PostgreSQL</ulink>)
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/simplexml">SimpleXML</ulink>
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/spl">SPL</ulink>
				(Standard PHP Library)
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/xsl">XSL</ulink>
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>The database extension is only required if your project
		requires a database.</para>

		<para>There's a driver available for most databases, including
		PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite, Oracle, MSSQL. PDO is also supported
		and all the PDO drivers are expected to work.</para>

		<para>The following extensions are required by some of the less
		used features of the framework, but you might not need them:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/curl">CURL</ulink>
				for the QUnit test suite
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/fileinfo">fileinfo</ulink>
				for file management in the extra library
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/imap">IMAP</ulink>
				for IMAP mailboxes access
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/intl">intl</ulink>
				for localization
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Finally, the following extensions are highly recommended:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/apc">APC</ulink>
				for file and data cache
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				<ulink url="http://php.net/gettext">gettext</ulink>
				for faster string translation functions
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>If you intend to generate PDF files, you will be required to
		add the <command>pdflatex</command> command to your PATH. This command
		can be found in the texlive package, or in any other LaTeX
		distribution.</para>

		<para>If your application needs to send emails, you'll want to install
		an MTA at least in the production environment. We recommend
		<application>postfix</application> as it doesn't require any particular
		configuration if you only need to send emails.</para>

		<para>You will also need <application>git</application> if you plan to
		download the framework using git.</para>

		<para>The following command will install all the essential packages on
		a newly installed Ubuntu Hardy server:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>apt-get install apache2 php5 php5-cli php5-pgsql php5-xsl postgresql make git-core curl</userinput></screen>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-install-before">
		<title>Preliminary considerations</title>

		<para>Before performing any configuration you should probably ask
		yourself a few questions about your project. These considerations
		are applicable for both new and existing projects.</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
				What environment am I targeting?
				Development, test, production?
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				What web server am I using?
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				Does the project use a database?
				Do I have the connection information?
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
				Does the project need any cron jobs installed?
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Some of those considerations will be walked through in the
		following chapters. We'll explain the more general configuration
		right away though.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-install-webserv">
		<title>Web server configuration</title>

		<para>The configuration depends on which web server you are using.
		Since all the developers are using Apache 2.2, we are going to explain
		how to configure it. Feel free to submit guidelines to get Web:Extend
		working with other web servers. See <xref linkend="ap-contrib"/>
		for more information.</para>

		<para>First of all it is recommended that you enable mod_rewrite. While
		not mandatory, mod_rewrite allows you to write clean URLs. No need to
		reload Apache yet, we still have to configure the site for the
		application:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>a2enmod rewrite</userinput>
Enabling module rewrite.
Run '/etc/init.d/apache2 restart' to activate new configuration!</screen>

		<note>
			<title>Development environment</title>

			<para>It is good practice to create a local domain name for each
			of the applications you are working on. A local domain name allows
			you to test the application just like it would be on the production
			server.</para>

			<para>While they were only tested on Ubuntu, the following
			guidelines should work for most unix systems. You only have to add
			a new local host to your <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file.
			Open it with the editor of your choice and add a line below the
			localhost one for your own local domain name:</para>

<screen>
127.0.0.1   localhost
<userinput>127.0.0.2   myapp</userinput></screen>

			<para>Use a different IP than localhost (or other domains you may
			have) so that Apache can distinguish between the two domains.
			If you're worried about conflicting domain names on your network,
			you can use <literal>myapp.localhost</literal> instead.</para>

			<para>Then configure Apache like you would otherwise, using the
			local domain name newly created.</para>
		</note>

		<para>We recommend that you configure Apache log files per application
		(or per domain if your site has multiple domains). This allows you to
		easily check for errors or generate stats for the application.</para>

		<para>The following file will configure the application
		<literal>myapp</literal> fully, by defining the folders, rewrite rules
		and log files. Don't forget to change the paths to the actual paths on
		your environment.</para>

		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
			href="examples/build/chap-install-apache.xml.xml"/>

		<para>This file should be saved in the
		<filename>sites-available/</filename> Apache subdirectory on
		Debian-based distributions. Then use the following command to enable
		the site:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>a2ensite myapp</userinput>
Enabling site myapp.
Run '/etc/init.d/apache2 reload' to activate new configuration!</screen>

		<para>On other systems you might have to append it to an existing
		configuration file. In this case no need to call
		<command>a2ensite</command>.</para>

		<para>Now that everything is set, reload Apache:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>/etc/init.d/apache2 reload</userinput>
 * Reloading web server config apache2               [ OK ]</screen>

		<para>If you made a mistake in the configuration, Apache will warn
		you and will ignore your request. Correct your errors and try again
		until you get it working.</para>

		<note><para>
			You can also use the <filename>.htaccess</filename> file available
			in the <filename>share/apache/</filename> folder of your Web:Extend
			installation. Note that it only defines the rules for URL
			rewriting, and it can be used when accessing the application as a
			subfolder of a domain. Still, it is recommended to configure a
			site in Apache directly.
		</para></note>

		<para>You also need to make sure the <filename>app/tmp/</filename>
		folder is writable by the web server. On Debian-based distributions,
		the following command can be ran from your project's folder:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>chown www-data:www-data app/tmp/</userinput></screen>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-install-db">
		<title>Database configuration</title>

		<para>Almost all projects require some form of database. Depending on
		your application you'll prefer one over another, but in general we
		tend to recommend PostgreSQL as it is a solid all-purpose open-source
		relational database available on all the common platforms. See
		<xref linkend="chap-install-db-pgsql"/>.</para>

		<caution>
			<para>You shouldn't use MySQL. MySQL can be used as a relational
			database, but it isn't very good at it. It will always impose some
			additional constraints, varying depending on the storage back end
			used. If you don't really need a relational database, MySQL can
			still be used, but we think that there's better alternatives
			available that you should consider.</para>
		</caution>

		<sect2 id="chap-install-db-mysql">
			<title>MySQL</title>

			<para>First you need to install the MySQL package. On Debian-based
			systems, the following command should do the trick:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>apt-get install mysql-server php5-mysql</userinput>
Setting up mysql-server ...</screen>

			<para>You will need to enter a password for the mysql
			<literal>root</literal> user.</para>

			<para>When the installation is completed, reload Apache, or PHP
			won't be able to use the newly installed extension.</para>

			<para>Then all you need is to create your database and create
			an user to access it through your application. This user should
			not be a superuser; it should only have access to the database
			for your application. The following commands create the database
			<literal>mydb</literal> and the user <literal>myuser</literal>
			with a password <literal>mypassword</literal>. The user will
			only be able to connect from <literal>localhost</literal>.</para>

<screen>
$ <userinput>mysql -u root -p</userinput>
Enter password: 
Welcome to the MySQL monitor.  Commands end with ; or \g.
Your MySQL connection id is 1
Server version: 5.0.51a-3ubuntu5.5 (Ubuntu)

Type 'help;' or '\h' for help. Type '\c' to clear the buffer.

mysql> <userinput>CREATE DATABASE mydb;</userinput>
Query OK, 1 row affected (0.00 sec)

mysql> <userinput>GRANT ALL ON mydb.* TO myuser@localhost IDENTIFIED BY "mypassword";</userinput>
Query OK, 0 rows affected (0.00 sec)

mysql> <userinput>\q</userinput>
Bye</screen>

			<para>You should now be able to connect to your newly created
			database.</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="chap-install-db-pgsql">
			<title>PostgreSQL</title>

			<para>To install PostgreSQL on a Debian-based system, please follow
			the guide. On other systems the installation and configuration should
			be relatively similar. Refer to your vendor's documentation for more
			information.</para>

			<para>First you need to install the PostgreSQL package, if you haven't
			done so already:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>apt-get install postgresql php5-pgsql</userinput>
Setting up postgresql ...</screen>

			<para>The latest stable version will be automatically installed. You
			will need to reload Apache for the changes to take effect. Then
			you need to create a database and a user to access it. All PostgreSQL
			administration operations can be performed directly from the
			postgresql system account. Just log on this account and create what
			you need:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>su - postgres</userinput>
$ <userinput>createdb mydb</userinput>
$ <userinput>createuser -P myuser</userinput>
Enter password for new role: 
Enter it again: 
Shall the new role be a superuser? (y/n) <userinput>n</userinput>
Shall the new role be allowed to create databases? (y/n) <userinput>n</userinput>
Shall the new role be allowed to create more new roles? (y/n) <userinput>n</userinput></screen>

			<para>It is recommended that the user of your application isn't a
			superuser. Remember, if there's a security vulnerability in your
			application and the attacker can execute any query he wishes,
			he would have access to all your databases on this server if you made
			a superuser. The easiest solution for a start is to grant all
			privileges on your database, although it's possible to further restrict
			the privileges depending on your application's needs.</para>

			<para>You can grant privileges to users using <command>psql</command>.
			<command>psql</command> is the PostgreSQL command-line shell, allowing
			you to write SQL queries directly.</para>

<screen>
$ <userinput>psql</userinput>
psql (8.4.2)
Type "help" for help.

postgres=# <userinput>GRANT ALL ON DATABASE mydb TO myuser WITH GRANT OPTION;</userinput>
GRANT
postgres=# <userinput>\q</userinput>
$ <userinput>exit</userinput></screen>

			<para>You should now be able to connect to the database
			<literal>mydb</literal> with the user <literal>myuser</literal> and the
			password you entered earlier.</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="chap-install-db-sqlite">
			<title>SQLite</title>

			<para>Web:Extend supports both versions 2 and 3 of SQLite. Note though
			that SQLite 3 can only be accessed through the PDO driver. We are
			recommending the use of SQLite 3 for your new developments.</para>

			<para>To install SQLite 2 on Debian-based systems, use the following
			command:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>sudo apt-get install php5-sqlite</userinput></screen>

			<para>There's only one little difference for SQLite 3:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>sudo apt-get install php5-sqlite3</userinput></screen>

			<para>Don't forget to reload Apache to load the extensions after the
			installation completed.</para>

<!-- TODO: help about setting up and handling the database -->
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="chap-install-rm-examples">
		<title>Examples removal</title>

		<para>Depending on the package you downloaded, Web:Extend will
		feature examples as the default application. You can take a look
		at them by pointing your browser to the website URL you previously
		configured (<literal>http://myapp/</literal> in our example).
		When you are done with them, you'll probably want to start
		using the framework.</para>

		<para>Thankfully the examples are included as an addon. Therefore they
		can be removed with a single command:</para>

<screen>
# <userinput>php addons.php -r examples</userinput></screen>

		<note><para>
			Many components of the Web:Extend framework are simply addons.
			For an explanation of addons installation, removal and maintenance,
			please see <xref linkend="chap-addons"/>.
		</para></note>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
